<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The peace-maker or, a brief motive to unity and charitie in religion. By W.P. D.D.</title>
            <author>W. P.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 50 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A74652</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P135</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1417_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R209452</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99868335</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99868335</idno>
            <idno type="VID">169935</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A74652)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 169935)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 182:E1417[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The peace-maker or, a brief motive to unity and charitie in religion. By W.P. D.D.</title>
                  <author>W. P.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 94 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.W. for John Place, and are to be sold at his shop at Furnifals-Inne gate,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Nouember 3".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Peace --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Religious tolerance --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:169935:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE PEACE-MAKER, OR A brief Motive to Unity and Charitie in Religion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> W.P.D.D.</p>
            <q>Bleſſed are the Peace-makers, for they ſhall be called the Children of God, <bibl>
                  <hi>Mat. 5.9.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T.W.</hi> for <hi>John Place,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at <hi>Furnifals</hi>-Inne gate, 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:169935:2"/>
            <p>Theſe Books are to be ſold in <hi>Edinburgh</hi> at <hi>Thomas Wylie</hi> his Shop, over againſt the Old Church-Style.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:169935:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:169935:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:169935:3"/>
            <head>THE Peace-Maker, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T was the adviſe, good Chriſtian Reader, of the Prophet <hi>Jeremy,</hi> run to &amp; fro through the ſtreets of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and ſeek in the broad places therof, if ye can find a man, <hi>Jr.</hi> 1.5.
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:169935:4"/>They were not ſo much troubled there to find out a man, as we ſhall be now to find out a Chriſtian. We ſo buſie our ſelves a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Controverſies, that we forget to be good Chriſtians. There was a time indeed when the name was firſt given at <hi>Antioch, Act.</hi> 11.26. that it was then well ſet by; but this laſted not long, for preſently after they fell a ſiding amongſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:169935:4"/>and one cryed I am of <hi>Paul,</hi> another I am of <hi>Apollos,</hi> and another I am of <hi>Cephas,</hi> and another I am of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12. and much adoe had St. <hi>Parl</hi> to appeaſe theſe factions: for preſently af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter they fell to them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and have ſo conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, yea, and increaſed in them even unto this day. <hi>But Chriſt is not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided,</hi> ſaith the ſame Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, neither is this to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:169935:5"/>Chriſt the God of love and peace, who lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved us when we were his enemies; and the Apoſtle makes a good inference of imitation upon it, 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.11. <hi>Beloved, if God ſo lovedus, we ought alſo to love one another:</hi> Nay, as though there were nothing elſe required of a good Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, and a fellower of Chriſt, our Saviour ſaith, <hi>Joh.</hi> 13.15. <hi>by this ſhall all men know you are my d ſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:169935:5"/>if you have love one to another.</hi> Seeing then this is the proper and peculiar badge and cogniſance of a diſciple of Chriſt to love his fellow-diſciples, What argument would be fitter here to treat of, than a perſwaſion to all Chriſtians to be in peace and charity one with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother?</p>
            <p>But alas how unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a task is it, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat of Peace and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty!
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:169935:6"/>For he that goes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to part a fray, in all likelyhood will have blowes on both ſides, eſpecially where the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſites and combatants are fierce and violent; he that is eager on any one ſide, ſhall be ſure to find ſome faſt friends, but he that bewaileth the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable diſtraction of the whole, and doth but ſet a foot forward to make up the breach, will find few
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:169935:6"/>to take his part, but ſhall be ſure to have many a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout his ears: And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may obſerve that preſently after our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our had ſaid, <hi>Bleſſed are the Peace-makers, Mat.</hi> 5.9, 10. he immediatly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, <hi>Bleſſed are they that are perſecuted for righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ſake;</hi> knowing well enough, that if a man will undertake to be a Peace-maker, hee muſt preſently prepare to ſuffer
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:169935:7"/>perſecution, and I know none greater than that of Peace-makers in religion, for they ſuffer on all ſides, either by ſharp and bitter words, or by ſcoffing and jeering ſpeeches. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the hot-ſpurs of theſe times be at deadly fewd and bitter enmity one with another, yet will they, like <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate,</hi> joyn together and muſter up their forces againſt thoſe who labour any
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:169935:7"/>kind of pacification, and deſire to be quiet in the land. <hi>Woe is me</hi> (ſaith <hi>David,</hi> Pſal. 120.4, 5, 6. (<hi>that I am conſtrained to dwell with</hi> Meſech, <hi>and to have mine habitation amongſt the tents</hi> Kedar: <hi>my ſoul hath long dwelt among them that be enemies unto peace. I la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour for Peace, but when I ſpeak unto them thereof, they make them ready to Battell.</hi> Never could the pious and peaceable Soul more
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:169935:8"/>truly cry out than now, <hi>My mothers Children were angry with me. Cant.</hi> 1.5. A ſtrange ſpeech to call them <hi>Mothers children:</hi> had it not been a more eaſie and familiar way to ſay, my Brethren or my Siſters were angry with me (for ſo they muſt be, if they were her Mothers Children) why then doth ſhe make ſuch an invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſpeech of it, <hi>My mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers children were angry
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:169935:8"/>with me?</hi> True indeed, though they ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not chooſe but be her Brethren, (as being her Mothers chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren) yet ſhe doth not, ſhe dares not call them Brethren, for they will not acknowledge it, they hate the name of Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and make them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves profeſſed enemies, and therefoe ſhe is forced to leave out this loving and affectionate compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of brethren, and
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:169935:9"/>ſay in a kind of ſtrange phraſe, <hi>My mothers children were angry with me.</hi> Yet ſhould no man be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged from perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo worthy a duty; for though there be a perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution that attends upon Peace makers here, yet is there a bleſſing promiſed them hereafter. And ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our bleſſed Lord and Maſter Chriſt Jeſus, when he was about to leave his Apoſtles and Diſciples,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:169935:9"/>left unto them this gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den legacy, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.27. <hi>Peace I leave with you, my peace I give unto you,</hi> O how well would it become all of us to be men of Peace, the Miniſters to preach for the Peace of <hi>Jeruſalem, the people to pray for the peace of Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, for they ſhall proſper that love it.</hi> Pſal. 122.6.</p>
            <p>I will begin this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation unto Peace and Charity, from that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:169935:10"/>name which we all acknowledge, in that we are called Chriſtians, and doe all pretend to imitate Chriſt in our doctrine and practice. There was a time indeed when this name was much taken notice of, and great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for any man to own it, when they had no other argument then, nor any other cauſe of their cruell perſecutions, but to hear a man confeſſe <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianus
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:169935:10"/>ſum,</hi> I am a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: But when theſe ſtorms were blown over, and the Church began to be in peace, this name of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian was not ſo much regarded. And yet me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks the very name of Chriſtian is not altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be contemned, for, unleſſe I am deceived, whoſoever hath but this appellation may chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge a brotherhood with me, for in Scripture I find
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:169935:11"/>a brother and a Chriſtian to be the very ſame, ſo that whoſoever is a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian will neceſſarily be my brother. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.12, 13. <hi>If any brother hath a wife,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>that believeth not, and ſhe be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to dwell with him, let him not put her away; and if the woman hath an husband which believeth not, if he be pleaſed to dwell with her, let her not leave him: But if the unbelieving depart, let
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:169935:11"/>him depart, a brother or a ſiſter is not to bondage in ſuch caſes.</hi> Where the Apoſtle plainly ſheweth that a brother and a ſiſter are ſuch as are Chriſtians, and oppoſite only to Infidels and unbelievers. Neither ought we to take that exhortation of Saint <hi>Paul</hi> 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.17. when he ſaith, <hi>love the brotherhood,</hi> in any narrower ſenſe, but that we ſhould love every one that is a Chriſtian, not
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:169935:12"/>only becauſe he agreeth with me in ſome opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons concerning religion, but I ought to love him in that reſpect he is a Chriſtian, and profeſſeth Chriſt crucified. Neither ought we to love him thus with an ordinary kind of love, in wiſhing him well, and doing him good, for ſo we ought to love and doe good to all, but there is a more ſtrict tie of love that lies upon
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:169935:12"/>us Chriſtians one to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; and therefore al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Apoſtle wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth us <hi>to doe good to all men, yet eſpecially tot he houſhold of faith, Gal</hi> 6 10. that is, to ſuch as be Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>Were this precept of the Apoſtle practiſed as it ought to be, there would not be ſo much unchari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tableneſs, nor peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo much diſſention amongſt Chriſtians. Why can we not conſider one
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:169935:13"/>another as united in this bleſſed name of <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and ſet aſide for a time thoſe names of faction &amp; diviſion? why ſhould we not rejoyce awhile in thoſe things wherein we agree, and not alwaies be wrangling about thoſe things wherein we differ? Of what moment thoſe opinions are wherein we diſagree I am not able to determine; this I dare be bold to ſay, that the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:169935:13"/>points wherein we are friends, are of far greater conſequence, than thoſe are wherein we fall out. And yet we ſo eagerly contend one with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and damn each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the pit of hell, as though our differences were very important, and our agreement not worth the talking of. For my part I ſhould be loath to exclude any viſible Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church from all
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:169935:14"/>hopes of ſalvation, and if I muſt needs offend, I had rather give account to a mercifull God for too much mildneſs and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, than too much fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and ſeverity: yet I hope to make it appear, that my opinion of Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity ſhall not exceed the bounds of verity.</p>
            <p>A chief cauſe of the continuance of theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentions is, that men mind not ſo much the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:169935:14"/>common cauſe of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, as their own particular engagements, nor ſtudy how they may agree one with another, as how to uphold the ſide they are on: whereas would they ſet aſide pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice and partiality, and caſt an equall eye upon all the Churches, they would not ſpy ſo many faults abroad, and ſo few at home, but would free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confeſs there might be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:169935:15"/>greater concord amongſt Chriſtians than now there is. No other Unity doe I labour for at this time but that of Charity, that Chriſtians would not for ſome differences in opinion, pronounce ſuch an heavy ſentence upon one another, as is that of Damnation. If God ſhould deal with us as wee deal with one another, if he ſhould cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure us all as we cenſure
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:169935:15"/>one another, I know not who ſhould be ſaved: The Papiſt damning the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, and ſome among us the Papiſts, and both of them any other that ſhall differ from them both. But my hope is, and my hearty prayer to God ſhall be, that he would be more mercifull to all theſe, than they are one to another. When I conſider with my ſelf the manifold diſtractions of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:169935:16"/>Chriſtians about Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the great fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and violence uſed on all ſides, every one think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own opinion tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, and conſequently damning all others that differ from him, I could not but call to mind that prophecy of our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>Mat.</hi> 24.12. con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe latter and worſer times, <hi>Becauſe ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity ſhall abound</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the love of many ſhall
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:169935:16"/>waxe cold:</hi> for although Charity of it ſelf be of a hot and diffuſive nature, yet now clean contrary to the nature of it, it is in moſt men grown cold; it being the nature of cold to contract and combine, to congeal and draw into a narrow room; thus is it now with our Charity. For whereas like the heat in our naturall bodies, it ſhould diffuſe it ſelf into all the members thereof,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:169935:17"/>unto the whole Chriſtian Church, yet I know not how it hath taken cold, for men contract their love now into a very ſmall compaſs and nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row room, that is, to no more than to ſuch who jump with them in the ſame Opinion about Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, leaving others who differ from them, to nothing but death and damnation. For not only in ſeverall Countries, but
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:169935:17"/>in the ſame Kingdome, in the ſame City, nay in the ſame Family, there are ſeverall Religions, or at the leaſt ſeveral Opinions about Religion reigning: So that what Saint <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> complained of in his time, is truly verified in theſe, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 147. <hi>Thou ſeeſt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>with how great and miſerable diſtraction Chriſtian houſes and families are divided and troubled; husbands and wives can agree
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:169935:18"/>well enough to goe to bed together, bnt they cannot agree to goe to Chriſts Altar toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: There they ſwear peace one to another, but here they can have no peace. Parents and Children live well enough together in one houſe of their own, but one houſe of Gods will not hold them both. Their deſire is that thoſe ſhould ſucceed them in their own inheritance, who yet they think have no inheritance with Chriſt. Maſters and ſervants
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:169935:18"/>divide the Common Lord and Maſter of us all, who yet took upon him the form of a ſervant, that ſo he might free all.</hi> I ſay never more fully verified than in theſe daies; For in how many families ſhall we obſerve this great diviſion? the Husband goes to Church, and the Wife ſtaies at home, or the Wife goes to Church, and the Husband ſtaies at home, and ſo between Parents &amp; Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:169935:19"/>Maſters and Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants. The Father will give his Son the por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his land, who yet thinks he ſhall have no portion in the land of the living.</p>
            <p>The great diviſion of the Chriſtian world, was firſt between the Eaſt and Weſt Churches, and this Weſt hath been ſince ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>divided into the Roman and the Reformed Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: So that the divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:169935:19"/>amongſt Chriſtians which is conſiderable, is but into three parts, the Eaſtern, the Romaniſt, and our Reformed. All Chriſtian Churches, and ſo far forth the members of them brethren and ſiſters; and not only Chriſtian Churches, but alſo Catholike and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox in theſe points wherein they agree one with another, and with the Primitive Church.
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:169935:20"/>Why may it not be with theſe Churches, as it was with thoſe ſeven Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>Aſia</hi> which S. <hi>John</hi> wrote unto, in which there were ſome things commendable, and other things amiſs? they were encouraged in the former, and reproved for the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. And although ſome of them were better than others, yet you ſhall ſacre find one of them to which he doth not ſay,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:169935:20"/>haben adverſus te pauca, I have a few things againſt thee: And yet we ſhall find that Chriſt himſelf was in the midſt of all theſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven churches, <hi>for he was in the midſt of the ſeven golden candleſticks,</hi> Revel. 1.13. <hi>and bad in his right hand ſeven ſtars,</hi> Rev. 1.16. For wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting to the Church of <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſus,</hi> he maketh this one of his attributes, <hi>Apoc.</hi> 21. <hi>Theſe things</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>who who holdeth the ſeven ſtars
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:169935:21"/>in his right hand, who walketh in the midſt of the ſeven gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Candleſticks.</hi> So that our Saviour walked in the midſt of all theſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, even in that luke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warm Church of <hi>Laodicea,</hi> which he threatned to ſpue out of his mouth. And let <hi>Rome</hi> tell us never ſo much of her infallibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and unerring chair, yet queſtionleſs there is none of our Churches, no not the beſt of them, that our
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:169935:21"/>Saviour may not ſay to her, <hi>habeo adverſus te pauca, I have a few things againſt thee.</hi> And as thoſe ſeverall Churches, though ſome of them very faulty, yet were all ſeverall members of Chriſt, and helped to make up one body: why may it not be ſo in theſe Churches I ſpeak of? For firſt they all agree in that one and only foundation of Religion, Jeſus Chriſt, as the Apoſtle calleth
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:169935:22"/>him, <hi>No other foundation can any other man lay, than that which is layd, to wit Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and this no doubt is a ſure and good foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and this maketh them to be Chriſtan Churches; they are all baptized into Chriſt, and look to be ſaved by his ſufferings: And think not this to be a ſmall matter; for St. <hi>Paul</hi> deſired to know nothing elſe, <hi>I e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:169935:22"/>know any thing among you but Jeſus Chriſt, and him cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,</hi> and it worked upon his affection as much as upon his underſtanding; <hi>God forbid that I ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſave in the croſſe of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> Gal. 6.14. that is in Chriſt crucified. Beſides this one foundation, they all embrace the two Teſtaments, the three Creeds, and the four firſt generall Councills, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:169935:23"/>many other very materiall points. The diſcord a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us Chriſtians hath been long agoe ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected to us; and certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly there hath nothing ſo much drawn ſome out of the Church, and kept o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers from comming into the Church, as theſe quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rels amongſt our ſelves; Unto whom I briefly an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer; If they like not our differences, let them joyn with us in thoſe things
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:169935:23"/>wherein we agree, and that is to be Chriſtians, to believe in Chriſt and him crucified, and thoſe other principall points where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of I ſpake, and to ſtrive to imitate Chriſt to their power, and then our diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords will leſs trouble them. It is true, we have not all built alike upon this foundation, but ſome no queſtion have built wood and ſtraw, as well as ſilver and gold; yet all
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:169935:24"/>of us no doubt do ſtrive to imitate Chriſt as neer as we can, both in our do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, and in our practice: and certainly in theſe ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtructures of Religion, good intentions muſt go far, or elſe it will go hard with many of us; not that they altogether excuſe the fault, but doubtleſs they take off much from the puniſhment. There is a difference between the Eaſt and Weſt Churches,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:169935:24"/>in what kind of bread the Euchariſt is to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; the Eaſt receiving in unleavened bread, the Weſt in leavened bread. And herein though they differ among themſelves, yet they both ſtrive to i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitate Chriſt, becauſe the one Church thought our Saviour uſed then the bread that was leavened, the other, that which was unleavened. Either Church is the leſs blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:169935:25"/>becauſe they think both, that they follow our Saviours example.</p>
            <p>S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner doth prettily recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile a difference between ſome concerning the time how often we ſhould receive the holy Sacrament of the Lords Supper; for ſome it ſeems in his time thought we were bound to receive the Euchariſt every day, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers but now and then
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:169935:25"/>
               <hi>Some</hi> (ſaith he <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 118.) <hi>communicate daily, others but upon certain daies; ſome will omít no day, others will only receive on the Sabbath, and the Lords day. There is a freedome to be uſed in both theſe. Some will ſay we muſt not daily receive the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, becauſe we ought to ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect and ſet apart ſome daies wherein we muſt live more carefully and religiouſly, and ſo come to the Sacrament more worthily, and with greater
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:169935:26"/>devotion: On the other ſide, another tells us, yea, but if the plague ſore of ſin, and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence of the diſeaſe beſo great and dangerous, ſuch ſoveraign medicines as theſe are not to be deferred. Of both theſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>Iet every man take his choice, and do that which he thinks in his conſcience he may best and moſt piouſly perform; for neither of theſe diſhonour the body and blood of our Saviour, but rather both of them do ſtrive to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:169935:26"/>this ſaving Sacrament. For</hi> Zacheus <hi>rejoyced great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to entertain our Saviour in his houſe. The Centurion ſaid, Lord, I am not worthy thou ſhouldeſt come under my roof; both of theſe did worſhip and honour our Saviour, though after a diverſe, and as it were a contrary manner, both of them being miſerable by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of ſin, both of them obtain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mercy for their ſins. Thus one man to honoun Chriſt dares not receive every day,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:169935:27"/>another alſo to honour Chriſt dares not omit any day.</hi> And although theſe be but pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty differences, yet why may I not apply it to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſies of greater mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, eſpecially ſeeing that ancient Father S. <hi>Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vian, lib.</hi> 5. <hi>de Providentia;</hi> hath found a good inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the <hi>Arians,</hi> the moſt pernitious and moſt dangerous hereticks ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted that ever have been in the Church: <hi>They
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:169935:27"/>whom we account hereticks</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>account not them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves hereticks, for they ſo much eſteem themſelves good Catholicks, that they defame us with the note and appella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hereſie. That therefore which they be to us, the very ſame are we to them. We are certain that they injure the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine generation, in that they ſay, the Son is leſſe and infe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rior to the Father: They think us likewiſe injurious to the Father, becauſe we make
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:169935:28"/>the Son equall unto him. The true honour of God is among ſt us, but they think that to be the honour of the Deity, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve as they believe. They are undutifull, but they think it the greateſt duty of their Religion. They are impious, but they think this to be true piety. They erre therefore, but they erre with a very good mind and intention, not with a hatred, but with a good affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction towards God; verily be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving that they honour and
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:169935:28"/>love God. Although they have not the right Faith, yet they notwithſtanding think this to be perfect love towards God. In what manner they ſhall be puniſhed in the day of Judgement for this very er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of falſe opinion, no man can tell but the Judge him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A good leſſon for the hot-ſpurs of theſe times, with who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it is a very ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie matter to pronounce damnation upon the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:169935:29"/>leaſt diſagreement in Religion, whereas this good Father would not determine any thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe great here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks the Arrians, but leaves them to the mercy of the Judge, not being able to diſcern what they did deſerve. You ſee that this holy Father finds out a good intention even in theſe hereticks. And if there was a good intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on amongſt thoſe that
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:169935:29"/>were ſo groſsly erroneous, why may there not be good intentions found out amongſt us alſo, who are not at ſuch great odds, and acknowledged on all ſides to have no ſuch dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous opinions amongſt us.</p>
            <p>I ſpeak not this any whit to countenance that opinion of the Arrians, which is creeping into the Church again, but leave them to ſtand or
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:169935:30"/>fall to their own maſter, and ſhall in the mean time be perſwaded that they goe not againſt their conſciences, and ſo farre forth it will goe better with them: yet with this holy Father, not free them from puniſhment, but muſt refer the maner and meaſure thereof to the time of Judgement.</p>
            <p>Thoſe of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> are ſo impatient of this doctrine, that they
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:169935:30"/>care not for being ſaved, unleſs they may be ſaved alone; And their writers generally agree upon no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo much, as that out of their Communion there is no Salvation. One of their late writers, (<hi>Barckly Paren. li.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 1.) can profeſs thus, <hi>We</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>proclaim with the whole Church, and we command with</hi> Moſes <hi>that Heaven and Earth would hear us, that there is no communion
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:169935:31"/>between God and Belial, &amp; that theſe Protestants doe ſo far differ from us in matters of faith, that they altogether in vain expect thoſe manſions of happineſs which are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for us.</hi> And after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he ſaith, <hi>He that dares believe a ſtubborn and obſtinate Proteſtant can be ſaved, doth by ſo believing fall from the Catholick Faith. And that this is no private or obſcure ſentence of the Church, but that all Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholicks
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:169935:31"/>are of the ſame mind, that none of them are ignorant if it, nor any can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble it, unleſs he be an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expert Divine, or for fear on ambition preſfers ſome mens favour before the truth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Another of their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany <hi>Camp. rat.</hi> 10. avers the ſame, with a very great and ſolemn proteſtation, <hi>I call to witneſs</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>Gods throne, and that tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall at which I ſhall ſtand to give an accompt of theſe my
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:169935:32"/>reaſons, and of whatſoever I have ſpoken or done, that either there is no heaven at all, or that it peculiarly and proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly belongs unto us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>I' Campian,</hi> muſt ye be ſaved, and none but yee? what is not Heaven able to hold us as well as you? Or will our ſalvation be any diſparagement to yours? It ſeems it will. But to come a little clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer to you: Is it nothing with you at one breath,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:169935:32"/>to throw ſo many ſouls headlong to Hell, for whom Chriſt died; and which is more who are already incorporate into Chriſt by Baptiſm? It coſt more to redeem their ſouls; but you will let that alone for ever. Our comfort is that though you paſs ſuch ſentence upon us here, yet you are not to be our Judges hereafter, but muſt your ſelves come to give an
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:169935:33"/>account as well as we, and peradventure of theſe ſpeeches. Account us not men of ſo deſperate and deplored an eſtate that we would wittingly and willingly run into hell: why ſhould not our ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation be as dear unto us, as yours is unto you? or why ſhould you not think us to have as great a care of our ſalvation, as you have of yours? For could we be perſwaded
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:169935:33"/>that we were inheriſie, and that there is no ſalvation out of your Church, how quickly would we fly unto you? How gladly would we be entertained by you? what means and moans would we make to be members of your ſociety? Who can endure ſuch peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory pronunciations of Judgement of God's e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall wrath and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation upon us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:169935:34"/>fore we come to our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring? And ſeeing, <hi>God's mercy is over all his works, who can endure that you ſhould interdict God's mercy, and judge what the ſentence of the Judge ſhall be, before the day of judgement. So that if God had a mind to ſpare ſuch ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners</hi> (as you ſay wee poor Proteſtants are) <hi>yet by your verdict and preſcription hee could not be ſuffered to do it as S.</hi> Jerom <hi>long ago complained of</hi> Critobulus <hi>the Pelagian.
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:169935:34"/>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>adverſ. Pelag.</hi> Were we ſuch tares in the field of the Church, as you would make the world believe, yet if you would imitate Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. you ſhould let us grow till the har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt, leſt you pluck up the good corn with us.</p>
            <p>Neither are you thus fierce alone, there are ſome of our own ſide, to requite you in your own kind, are as confiden-that you cannot be ſaved,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:169935:35"/>as you are that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not; ſo that the Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on now is, In which of our two Churches ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is to be had? For taking it for granted that we have excluded all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and got Heaven between us, we cannot be content to ſhare it, but we muſt confine and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſs it to one of our Churches, as though it could not be had in both, nay as though it could
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:169935:35"/>not be had out of both; for I am verily perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and dare undertake to make it good, that thoſe poor Eaſtern Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, who differ from us both, will yet come to Heaven aſſoon as either of us; vvich vvere it vvell conſidered, might bee a good means to pacifie this Queſtion, and to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate the heat of many more betvveen us.</p>
            <p>But this monopolizing
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:169935:36"/>of Chriſt, although it be generally entertain'd by the Roman Partie, yet are not all our reformed Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines ſo ſtrait lac'd, but many of them, and thoſe of no ſmall note can be content that others ſhould be ſaved with them, and therefore they are called by you, by way of deriſion, <hi>good fellow Chriſtians. As though they had ſo much of the good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in them, that they have
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:169935:36"/>too little of the good Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an.</hi> And indeed you have moſt reaſon to be angry with theſe good fellow Chriſtians, for they are like to doe you all the miſchief, for having found that there may be ſalvati on in our Church as well, yea, with more eaſe than in yours, we ſhall never be thinking of going any further. As for thoſe who are ſo eager, that will conſine ſalvation to one
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:169935:37"/>certain Church, you have ſome hope of them, that in time they may come over to you: And what you object to us as a crime, we eſteem as our great glory, and account it one of God's ſpecial bleſſings, that we live in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of a Church, that is ſo charitable, and we are willing to have ſo much of the good fellow in us, becauſe we would not have too little of the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:169935:37"/>good Chriſtian: for though our Creed bee compris'd in a narrow room, yet our charity ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends farre, not only to you, but the Eaſtern Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We have a little Siſter, and ſhe hath no breaſts, what ſhall we do for our Siſter, in the day when ſhe ſhall be ſpoken of? We have a little Siſter. Cant.</hi> 8.8. Though the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> call the Church of Greece Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:169935:38"/>and Schiſmaticall, yet we of the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> eſteem her to be a Daughter of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Church, and our Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, though now ſhe be little, yet ſhe was a great one, not inferiour any waies to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſhe brought forth many Children, and gave Milk plentifully; but now alas ſhe is little, by reaſon of her long perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution, and her breaſts
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:169935:38"/>dried up, for now ſhe is in a manner barren, and able to bring forth but few Children. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though She be in this poor and deſolate eſtate, yet the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> will doe nothing for her, for when at the Councell of <hi>Florence</hi> ſhe deſired aid of them againſt the Turks, they gave her no ſuccour at all, but left her in mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie here, and adjudged her as they doe us to death
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:169935:39"/>and damnation hereafter. <hi>What ſhall we do for our Siſter?</hi> ſo long as we ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge her for our Siſter, we ſhould be wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to doe ſomething for her <hi>in the day when ſhe ſhall be ſpoken of;</hi> for as yet no body ſpeaks for her, no body laments her, but lets her alone, as if ſhe deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved no pitty, no ſuccour, no commiſeration, the Romaniſts have perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſo many that ſhe is
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:169935:39"/>ſchiſmaticall and hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call in her tenents. But all thoſe who eſteem of her as a ſiſter, I hope will doe ſomething for her in the day when ſhe ſhall be ſpoken for, when her cauſe ſhall be pleaded, and ſhe cleared from holding ſuch dangerous and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Doctrines, then certainly ſhe will have many to pitty her, many to help her.</p>
            <p>But the confining of
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:169935:40"/>ſalvation to your own Partie, hath not onely ſharpened the pens of many Writers to much bitterneſs and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning one another, but alſo hath unſheathed the ſwords of many Princes and Potentates to the great and lamentable ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of much Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an blood. S. <hi>Paul</hi> thought it a ſtrange thing in his time for a Brother to go to Law with a Brother:
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:169935:40"/>
               <hi>I ſpeak to your ſhame</hi> (ſaith he.) <hi>Is it ſo that there is not a wiſe man amongſt you, no not one that is able to judge between his Brethren, but Brother goeth to Law with Brother, and that under the Infidels?</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.5.6. What if S. <hi>Paul</hi> had lived in theſe daies; wherein not only a Brother goeth to Law with a Brother, but a Brother goeth to War with a Brother, yea, and which is more, maketh
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:169935:41"/>that to be a motive unto his War, to wit, Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which ſhould be a forcible means of peace and reconcilement. <hi>Tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum religio potuit ſuadere malorum?</hi> Is it poſſible that Religion ſhould e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be the true Mother of ſo much miſchief? No, no, our true Mother the Holy Catholick Church doth not further ſuch de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, but lament them, and doth more juſtly
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:169935:41"/>complain then <hi>Rebecca</hi> did when twins ſtrove in her womb, <hi>ſeeing it is ſo, why am I thus.</hi> For ſhe could be content would her children but ſtrive, and ſtruggle one with another, but when they come to blows and blood, yea much effuſion of blood, as we ſee at this day, how can ſhe be but like <hi>Rabel weeping for her children and not be comforted becauſe they are not? Mat.</hi> 1.
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:169935:42"/>When was that ever more truly fulfilled then novv, <hi>they that kill you ſhall think they do God good ſervice! Ioh.</hi> 16.2. Do you not think you have done God good ſervice in thoſe many maſſacres in <hi>France,</hi> in every of which how many thouſands of poor Chriſtians have you ſwept away with ſuch a ſuddain deſtruction, that had they been willing, you gave them not ſo
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:169935:42"/>much time as to repent them of their Proteſtancy? Do you not think that you had done God good ſervice, if that horrible deſign of the Gun-pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der-Treaſon had taken effect, a prodigie not to be ſpoken of without horrour and amazement, void of all humanity as well as Chriſtianity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But do what you can, call us Heretiques, Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiques, and what other diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gracefull
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:169935:43"/>name you can in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent, impriſon us, baniſh us, ſtrangleous, ſtifle us, burn us, hang us, we are yet your Brethren.</hi> Certainly our Saviour never intended to begin or propogate his Church by this means, he could as eſily have ſent forth mighty men of war to compell others to believe in him, as poor Fiſhermen who catch none but ſuch as come to net, or are fairly allu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:169935:43"/>to lay hold on the bait. If this open hoſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty were uſed againſt the Turks, the common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of the Chriſtian name, there were ſome pretence for it; and therefore we read that <hi>Moſes, Exod.</hi> 2. when he ſaw the Iſraelite and the Egyptian fight, he did not ſay, why ſtrive you, but drew his ſword, and ſlew the Egyptian, but when he ſaw the two Iſraelites fight, he ſaid, <hi>ye
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:169935:44"/>are brethren why ſtrive ye.</hi> What a glorious ſight would it be to ſee the red Croſs once again advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced as it was in the daies of <hi>Conſtantine?</hi> and if we did not ſee it written in Heaven, I hope we ſhould find it true upon earth, <hi>in hoc ſigno vinces.</hi> Unto this holy war I ſuppoſe all they would come, who have promiſed to fight under Chriſt's ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. And ſet aſide for a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:169935:44"/>while this private intereſt of Proteſtant, and Papiſt, and Grecian, and Lutheran, and Calviniſt, and Arminian, and Socinian, and if there be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other diviſion amongſt us, and take upon us that gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall livery of Chriſtianity, and ſo joyn together to reſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cue our Brethren from that wild Boar of the Forreſt which hath laid waſt this goodly vine; and afterwards we might ſee how we could decide the Controverſies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Chriſtians: For who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is in the right, I hope we are all well enough per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that he is in the
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:169935:45"/>wrong. Could <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late,</hi> otherwiſe deadly ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies be made friends, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree together to condemn Chriſt, and ſhall not thoſe, who are already Brethren and therefore ſhould be friends, combine together to ſave Chriſt: I ſay to ſave Chriſt, for ſo long as we ſave and preſerve his members, wee ſave and preſerve him; but ſo long as we ſuffer his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers to be thus perſecuted and oppreſſed, hee cannot chooſe but ſuffer with them: But we in ſteed of bandying againſt the common enemy, muſter up our forces one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:169935:45"/>another, and find that to be true by lamentable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, there is no greater hatred then of Brethren that are fallen out.</p>
            <p>Seeing then that all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians are Brethren, I ſay Brethren, as having one Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of us all, Brethren as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving one Faith, one Lord, one Baptiſm, whereby wee are born into the Catholick Church, and one food by the Sacrament of the Euchariſt, which makes us grow to be perfect men in Chriſt; ſeeing we are all theſe waies Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, I may well ſay as <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> did, <hi>ye are Brethren why
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:169935:46"/>ſtrive ye?</hi> of if ye muſt needs be ſtriving about matters of Religion, ſtrive and <hi>ſtrive earneſtly for the Faith which was once delivered to the Saints. Jud.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>And becauſe I ſay we are Brethren, I would not have you think we like not the cauſe we have in hand, or that we are ready to yeeld unto you, and preſently joyn hands with you, as ſome of you Imagine, and many of our ſide cauſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſly ſuſpect, but this is all, we would have the breach no greater than it is, and would not have the world believe, becauſe we differ in ſome
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:169935:46"/>things, that we agree in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. And although we call you Brethren, we will not wink at your faults, or joyn with you in them, but this doth put us in mind to admoniſh you more gently of them as brethren, though you rage ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo fiercely againſt us, for by this means we ſhall expreſs our charity towards you, and ſo heap coals of fire upon your head. God, he knows we are far enough from yielding to you as Romaniſts, yet ſhould we not be charitable to you as Chriſtians, we were much to blame. But ſee how you mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake, or rather indeed pervert
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:169935:47"/>and abuſe this our charity: <hi>For</hi> (ſay you) <hi>by your own acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgement, there may be ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in our Church, but we all deny there can be Salvation in yours, therefore all if they had care of themſelves would have recourſe to us, for it is the ſafer way to be a member of that Church, where both ſides yeeld there may be ſalvation, then in that where on ſide denies it.</hi> This were ſomething if Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation or Damnation depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon opinion, but I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe that charitable opinion, of ours, in hoping you may be ſaved, makes you never a whit the neerer heaven, but our
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:169935:47"/>ſelves; &amp; that rough cenſure of yours in ſetting us all out for damnation, makes us no whit the neerer hel, but your ſelves. And I had rather be a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of that Church, which holds there may be Salvation in both, then of that which holds there can be ſalvation but in one. For holding with the firſt, I am ſafe whereſoever I am, but holding with the latter, I muſt be in danger whereſoever I am. I ſay, whereſoever I am; for I am not onely in danger of my ſalvation, if I be in that Church wherein I think there is no Salvation, but alſo if I be
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:169935:48"/>in that Church out of which I think there can be no Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; becauſe I confine Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to one of theſe, which though I think it be in this a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, yet it may be in the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alone; this may ſuffice to ſatisfie that great Argument of our Adverſaries, wherein they ſo much glory, and if it be poſſible to moderate their ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity againſt us.</p>
            <p>Many other motives unto Charity might be ſhewed, but theſe briefly ſhall ſuffice. The one is, that we are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, and therefore brethren, and ſo ought to love as bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren; Another is, in that I
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:169935:48"/>hope our intentions are good, and that none maintains a falſe opinion perverſly againſt his conſcience.</p>
            <p>Now let me ſay unto all Chriſtians, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> doth to the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11, 12, 13. <hi>O ye Chriſtians, our mouth is open unto you, and not only ſo, but our heart is enlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged,</hi> not only to the Roman, but even to the Eaſt Church, and to as many as call upon the name of our Lord Jeſus. <hi>Ye are not ſtraitned in us, but ye are ſtraitned in your own bowels, now for a recompence in the ſame, I ſpeak unto you as unto Brethren, be ye alſo en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged!</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="92" facs="tcp:169935:49"/>
            <p>Let me beſpeak all learned Prelats and Paſtors on all ſides, as S. <hi>Auſtine Epiſt.</hi> 147. doth <hi>Proculianus,</hi> a Biſhop, and a favourer of the Donatiſts, <hi>I pray and beſeech thee</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>if there be any good diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition in thee, which many doe extoll, and command, if it be not a counterfeit courteſie by reaſon of worldly honour, that the tender bowells of pitty and compaſsion begin to yerne in thee, and that you would have theſe controverſies diſcuſsd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween us at the length, not by wrangling and railing one at another, but by fervent prayers and earneſt ſupplications unto
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:169935:49"/>Almighty God, and by compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all things peaceably, and examining them in the ſpirit of meekneſs, leſt the poor igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant people which now yeeld to, and willingly obey our juriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and command over them, preſs us with this their ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and dutifull obedience to us in the day of the Lord Jeſus,</hi> and ſay, they did as their lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders directed them, <hi>but rather by our unfeigned love and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, being together with us drawn from thoſe by-paths of errour and diſſention, they ſhould be directeed into the right way of truth and peace.</hi> I will concude all with this
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:169935:50"/>prayer, that it would <hi>pleaſe God to inſpire continually the Univerſall Church, with the ſpirit of truth, unity and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, and grant that all they who do confeſs his holy name, may agree in the truth of his holy word, and live in unity and godly love!</hi> And although we cannot at the firſt attain to that perfection to be of one mind, yet let us begin to be charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and bear with one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for who knows but that by entertaining this bond of peace, we may in good time come to the unity of the ſpirit; which he heartily wiſheth, and daily prayeth for, who is</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in Chriſt,</hi> W.P.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:169935:50"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
